One. Four, five. Fourteen.
As for the book. I’m going to tell it. They made this into a book, and when he sent it to be printed, Américo. But when he got older, he saw what he thought were mistakes. So, we had already been living for some time on Madison Street, West Madison. He brought us a big box, full.
He told my wife that he wanted us to keep them there until he had time to come back because he was in [inaudible], because he wanted to destroy them. My wife took out about 10 or 15 and hid them. I kept one; the others I think one of my brothers took one and another one too.
In some way a copy fell into the hands of Jesse Sloss and he told me he had it.
You know, I think he passed away, I think.
He already passed away? Was he sick?
Yes. I think so. I don’t know when, but I heard a gentleman who worked with him mentioned. Joe Rivera told me that, the county treasurer.
He was sick in his feet.
Yes, yes.
I saw him at the mall, him and his wife. He was married to Tencha. I think her name was Tencha Hinojosa. But I didn’t know he had died.
I think so. It seems so. I’ll find out, but I think so.
He told me he had a copy. As I say, I have one here, but I don’t know whether to lend it, to allow you all to take a picture of the photo that’s there because according to Américo he didn’t like it anymore when he got older. He was embarrassed for people to read those verses of a boy in love.
He wanted to destroy everything, but I kept one. I have it there. I don’t know whether to allow you to take a picture of that photo. Because it’s large.
If there’s going to be a problem, just the photos you allow us, that’s fine. Because we don’t want you to get upset with him.
Yes, because if I allow you… I’m going to show it to you, but I don’t want you to take a photograph because I don’t want any controversy. I don’t want him to get mad and all that.
Us neither. Better, if you don’t want to show it to me, I don’t even want to see it, that way there’s no problem. Just allow us what…
The ones I have there. The photographs I have there, I’ll show them to you in a moment. Mercedes!
I’ll bring them to you. They’re here on the table. Should I bring them?
Ah well, bring it to me.
Yes. All right.
They have a little paper, look, it’s there. He’s with his children and there’s the little paper, which is this one.
Very good. Thank you. We’ll start right now, Noro, whenever you’re ready.
Up there it was… There should be a page, a loose one.
Yes. This one. The one that isn’t in color.
What is that picture?
It’s a man and three children.
Is it Américo?
Yes. It’s Américo. It says, “January 1960”.
Nineteen hundred what?
60.
At Christmas. It says, “Christmas 59”. Yes, it must be Doctor Paredes.
Is it him and two children?
Yes. The three children. The two children, one older and one is in his arms, little, and another.
Are there others that Lydia looked for and are there?
Yes. They’re marked here. Very good.
Um, Mercedes? [Mercedes: Yes.] Bring me the book. The poems. [Mercedes: Okay]
You know you have these and there’s no problem, right, about making copies?
What?
I mean…
This? Yes.
Yes. That’s fine.
These are portraits he took with the family.
That’s fine.
What I’m going to show you is what’s in the book. Is that the portrait?
Yes.
It’s when he was young.
You know. Look, look at this picture, it’s great. You can’t take it but…
Some poems, some of them don’t have the date.
Yes. Let’s see. [Sound: Glass breaks off-screen]
What happened? Did something break?
Here it says, 3/1/36.
’36?
Here it has the information of the year, the month and the day he wrote the poem.
It says ’36?
Yes. ’36.
He was already 21 years old.
He was 21 years old?
Yes. Because he was born in ’15 and 10. 15 and 10, 25 and 5 is 30. It’s 15 and 6, 21. He was 21 years old. He was very young.
Look, yes. You have a few copies, right? These are some of the few copies that exist?
It’s the only one I know of. I think there was one in the Texas Southmost College Library, but I don’t know who saw it there.
Yolanda González should know if it’s there.
What...Yolanda González?
Yolanda González. She should know if it’s there or not.
She should know. It’s called… What does it say?
Cantos Adolescentes. You can get it there. I think it’s there.
All right. I’ll ask the doctor to see if he allows us to use it.
Yes.
Mr. Américo and three children at Christmas. It’s in black and white.
Well, do you want to take that one? Do you want that one? Look at the others that are there.
Yes. Here’s one. Doctor Paredes and I don’t know who this man with glasses is and two children. Could it be his wife?
Yes.
Is this his wife and two of the children?
Could be.
Here’s one I think with you. There are five men. This one on the left, I don’t know if it’s your father or who it might be.
There are five men?
Yes, there are five men. Three are on a sofa, and two are seated in front.
Are they in a house, in a residence?
In a house. There’s a painting behind them.
Ah, then they’re the… I had two brothers who were twins. Amador and Eleazar, and with Américo that made three. Eliseo made four and me, that’s five. It must just be us.
Well there are five, there are five.
There are five men?
Yes, the man in the middle has dark glasses.
It must be Eliseo, my brother. The oldest.
Are you on the right side? You’re wearing a tie. On the left side Mr. Paredes and his brothers here. What were the twins’ names?
Amador and Eleazar. They were twins. Amador was principal of Annie S. Putegnat.
Yes, that’s true.
Annie S. Putegnat. He died when he was principal there. He was principal there for 27 years.
Don’t you have photos of Mr. Paredes when he was in the military, in the army?
Of whom?
Of Mr. Américo when he was in the army.
You know, I do have some. I did have them, but my daughter didn’t find them. I had one where he was standing, in uniform with long pants. He’s alone, but I can’t find it.
You can’t find it. That’s fine. Here’s one I think from when he graduated from Texas. In June 1956.
Yes, doctor degree. It’s 1956, right?
1956, right.
Well, you can take that one.
He is in the center. You’ve got, I guess, the whole family there, or most of the family.
Yes, there’s Mom, my wife, Amador’s wife and Amador is there too.
Yes, there’s Amador.
There’s Amador and there’s Ofelia. There’s Herman [inaudible], who was principal of Pace High School. His wife is there too. Me and my wife. Mom and Américo with the cap and gown.
Yes, he’s got the cap and gown.
You can take this one too if you want.
All right. In a moment you’ll give us their information and he’ll take the photos of them individually over here.
Did you bring the camera?
Yes. We brought the camera. There’s a photo here that says 1944.
It’s Américo.
It’s a group of children. It looks like they’re at school. There are several here. I don’t know if one of you is here.
If it’s not marked with the paper I don’t think it’s Américo.
It’s not. That’s fine.
Lydia was the one who… Since I can’t see, Mrs. Olivares who is here has only been with us three years, she doesn’t know the whole family. Américo, I don’t think she’s seen him. She’s never seen him. Because he’s sick all the time, almost most of the time. He rarely comes here.
Did she mark any of the three or four photos?
She marked them with little slips of paper she had. The papers are still there.
Yes, are those the only ones you want us to take?
Yes, those are the ones she found.
All right… Here’s a lady named Liliana Longoria Garza or Diana Longoria Garza.
What’s her name?
Diana Longoria Garza.
The first name?
I can’t see because there’s a piece… It’s Juana Longoria Garza.
That sounds like Juanita, that’s my mother‑in‑law.
All right.
She’s an old lady now, right? Yes.
Is he sitting? Yes, he’s sitting. I think by the side of the road.
It doesn’t have a date or anything?
Nothing. It doesn’t.
I don’t know who it would be.
Don’t you have other books that…? I have several that Mr. Américo wrote. Some, for example, graduation invitations or something like that that…
Man, I think I do, but I’ll tell you it would take me a month.
Yes, to look for them?
Yes, because there are so many things we have here.
Yes, I understand. That’s fine. Is he about to turn 80?
Américo is 76. He was born on the 15th. Yes, he’s about to turn 80, right?
Yes, he’s going to turn 80.
In ’95 I’ll turn 80 in September. This September. In ’95 I’ll turn 80. Just on the 15th, 80, ’95. He’ll turn 80, he’s already 79.
Did you attend school here in Brownsville?
Who? What about it?
You. Did you go to school here in Brownsville?
Yes.
When did you graduate?
I didn’t graduate from high school here. I took an exam many years ago and passed it. The professor who was there, he must have been the dean, his name was Philips. Is he still there?
No, he’s not there. Yes. I…
You saw him there? Philips.
Yes, I worked with him.
He wanted me to register for… No, I told him. I’m already… it was, you’ll see, I think it was around…
’60. Around then. Because I went to Hammond. I had a lot of experience and I had read, I was working, I had worked in an Abstract? Company office and I had a lot of experience and practice in reading and interpreting legal documents and preparing legal documents.
By force—well, not by force, right? But I liked the work. I learned geometric formulas, how to get the length of a hypotenuse, get the volume of a cylinder, cubic inches and things like that I learned there on the job. I learned them just because I liked it. I have a book that, I’ll tell you the truth,
I never studied it, I tried to read it when my eyesight was already bad. It was a school text of an uncle of mine named José María Manzano, who was born in Bagdad, but not Baghdad in Iraq. No, Bagdad here on the river. At the mouth of the river. Bagdad here at the mouth of the river.
He was in school there and there he learned… There was a tower made of wood where they had the telegraph when he was a boy. That telegraph had two wires, they would send a message when a ship arrived and stopped way out there, because there was no port there. There was no entrance for ships.
A ship would come and arrive way out there; with a spyglass they would see its name. They would telegraph Matamoros and there in the telegraph office they would notify the merchants in Matamoros that a ship had arrived, two ships, three ships, from such‑and‑such place. The name.
They would head out from here in carts and in wagons and on horses to pick up the merchandise. Because they brought merchandise from Europe. Here in Brownsville it wasn’t [inaudible]. My uncle José was born there, he lived there, went to school there and left that little book, I have it. It’s more than 100 years old. Imagine.
I’ll bring it right now. Mercedes. Let’s see if she hears me. Mercedes?
All right. Mercedes, Mercedes?
Yes.
Mercedes, you know where it is, there in the drawer. I think it’s in the middle drawer of the dresser.
There’s a big envelope. There are two envelopes, in one of them there’s another envelope where I have the little book called Elements of Geometry.
Do you want me to bring it?
Bring it to me. There are other things there too. The document for Pedro is there.
Yes.
My grandfather grew up, was born here. His father’s name was Leandro Paredes. He had cows and horses, mares. There where… that’s what it was called at that time too. It’s still called La Parra Ranch. Have you heard of it?
Yes, I’ve heard of it.
Which is right in front of where it says Sarita. Because Sarita, Sarita Kennedy, was Don Gregorio’s daughter, and Don Gregorio was Mifflin’s son, the owner of that whole ranch, La Parra. My father Leandro, before Mifflin Kennedy came, first rented and then bought from an heiress,
a lady named Loreto Villarreal de Capteville. He bought the right she had in two grazing lands, the La Parra range and the El Infiernillo range. Which is attached; La Parra borders the Los Olmos creek, which is where Sarita is. There’s Riviera. The Los Olmos creek.
The other grazing land is called El Infiernillo, there where Riviera is. There my father Leandro bought what they called, they called it a right, and he bought La Parra too. There you go, this is it.
The book you mentioned?
Yes. Here it is.
Look.
Look at the dates, 1887, and it’s written on one of the pages by José. It says, “JM Manzano”. Manzano. Yes. Here it says Bagdad. Bagdad, 1887. ’87.
Yes. It says here.
It was the geometry textbook in Mexico and by the time they were in the fourth, fifth book they were already taking geometry.
Yes. [Laughter]
And here they weren’t. [Laughter]
No, here not until ninth or tenth. [inaudible]
Did you notice the cover, the inscription? It says JM Manzano.
Yes, JM Manzano. Bagdad.
[On screen: A color photo of younger Americo Paredes seated with his wife and two sons around a birthday cake.]
Bagdad. I was at Colegio San José… Mercedes? [The video cuts to black]